<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<LanguageData>
  
  <!-- EN: psylink -->
  <PsychicAmplifier.label>psylink</PsychicAmplifier.label>
  <!-- EN: An organic connection to a larger psychic field. This allows a person to psychically induce a distant archotech superintelligence to influence reality in ways that seem impossible.\n\nHigher levels of psylink permit the use of more powers. Regardless of psylink level, a person can only use specific powers that they have learned.\n\nPsylink comes from a variety of sources. Single-use psylink neuroformer devices can create a psylink. Tribal peoples also know how to develop it through ritual linking with the legendary anima tree.\n\nAs a physical phenomenon in the brain, psylink is poorly-understood by scientists, not least because it seems to actively conceal itself if studied too closely. One thing most agree on is that it somehow connects people to archotechs and harnesses their power, possibly through some sort of negotiation or sympathy mechanism. -->
  <PsychicAmplifier.description>Una connessione organica con un campo psichico più ampio. Ciò consente a una persona di indurre psichicamente una superintelligenza archotech distante ad influenzare la realtà in modi che sembrano impossibili.\n\nLivelli più alti di legame psionico consentono l'uso di più poteri. Indipendentemente dal livello di legame psionico, una persona può usare solo poteri specifici che ha appreso.\n\nIl legame psionico proviene da una varietà di fonti. I dispositivi neuroformer psylink monouso possono creare uno psylink. I popoli tribali sanno anche come svilupparlo attraverso il collegamento rituale con il leggendario albero dell'anima.\n\nIn quanto fenomeno fisico nel cervello, il collegamento psionico è poco compreso dagli scienziati, anche perché sembra nascondersi attivamente se studiato troppo da vicino. Una cosa su cui sono più d'accordo è che in qualche modo collega le persone agli archotecnici e sfrutta il loro potere, possibilmente attraverso una sorta di meccanismo di negoziazione o simpatia.</PsychicAmplifier.description>
  <!-- EN: Allows a person to psychically-induce an archotech to influence reality in ways that seem impossible. Higher levels of psylink permit the use of more powers. -->
  <PsychicAmplifier.descriptionShort>Consente a una persona di indurre psichicamente un archotech a influenzare la realtà in modi che sembrano impossibili. Livelli più alti di psylink consentono l'uso di più poteri.</PsychicAmplifier.descriptionShort>
  
</LanguageData>