<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<LanguageData>
  
  <!-- EN: baseliner -->
  <Baseliner.label>baseliner</Baseliner.label>
  <!-- EN: A naturally-evolved human with no major significant genetic modifications. -->
  <Baseliner.description>Un essere umano evoluto naturalmente senza significative modifiche genetiche.</Baseliner.description>
  
  <!-- EN: dirtmole -->
  <Dirtmole.label>talpa</Dirtmole.label>
  <!-- EN: With gray skin adapted to artificial light, they thrive in cramped and dark spaces where combat and travel happen over short distances. They are extremely capable at digging or mining tasks. In the open, however, they suffer from a sensitivity to light, slow speed and poor eyesight at distance.\n\nAfter the first tunnel colonies failed due to the stress of confinement, colonization agencies began genetically altering colonists to live without open space or sunlight. This xenotype is known colloquially as the dirtmoles. Today, dirtmoles have expanded out of their original tunnel homes and rule many confined spaces in the anthrosphere. They can be found in deep mines, cramped low-tech spacecraft, and teeming by the billions in the dark underlayers of countless urbworlds. -->
  <Dirtmole.description>Con la pelle grigia adattata alla luce artificiale, prosperano in spazi angusti e bui dove il combattimento e il viaggio avvengono su brevi distanze. Sono estremamente capaci di svolgere attività di scavo o estrazione mineraria. All'aperto, tuttavia, soffrono di sensibilità alla luce, lentezza e scarsa vista a distanza.\n\nDopo che le prime colonie nei tunnel fallirono a causa dello stress del confinamento, le agenzie di colonizzazione iniziarono ad alterare geneticamente i coloni per vivere senza spazi aperti o luce del sole. Questo xenotipo è conosciuto colloquialmente come talpe. Oggi, le talpe si sono espanse al di fuori dei loro tunnel originari e governano molti spazi ristretti nell’antroposfera. Possono essere trovate in miniere profonde, astronavi anguste a bassa tecnologia e a miliardi negli strati oscuri di innumerevoli mondi urbani.</Dirtmole.description>
  <!-- EN: With gray skin adapted to artificial light, dirtmoles thrive in cramped and dark spaces where combat and travel happen over short distances. They are naturals at digging and navigating complex tunnel structures. In the open, they suffer from a sensitivity to light, slow speed and poor eyesight at distance. -->
  <Dirtmole.descriptionShort>Con la pelle grigia adattata alla luce artificiale, le talpe prosperano in spazi angusti e bui dove il combattimento e il viaggio avvengono su brevi distanze. Sono naturali nello scavare e nel navigare complesse strutture di tunnel. All'aperto soffrono di sensibilità alla luce, lentezza e scarsa vista a distanza.</Dirtmole.descriptionShort>
  
  <!-- EN: genie -->
  <Genie.label>genio</Genie.label>
  <!-- EN: Designed to be engineers, genies' delicate bones and natural aptitude with machines allow them to manipulate devices with remarkable precision. They are emotionally cold and can follow orders where others might panic. However, they are fragile, and their amplified nerve impulses make them easy to debilitate with relatively little pain. With so much of their brains dedicated to analyzing machines, they lack the neural hardware to analyze emotions, so they sometimes come off as socially inept. Their dead calm makes it even harder for them to relate to what they see as madly-hotheaded baseliner humans.\n\nGenies were engineered thousands of years ago by a long-disbanded space navy to hold engineering positions on large starships. Today, genies still serve as engineers in great cities and fleets, but many can also be found working as lawyers, pilots, and musicians. -->
  <Genie.description>Progettati per essere ingegneri, le ossa delicate dei geni e la naturale attitudine con le macchine consentono loro di manipolare i dispositivi con notevole precisione. Sono emotivamente freddi e possono eseguire ordini laddove gli altri potrebbero farsi prendere dal panico. Tuttavia, sono fragili e i loro impulsi nervosi amplificati li rendono facili da debilitare con relativamente poco dolore. Con così tanto del loro cervello dedicato all’analisi delle macchine, mancano dell’hardware neurale per analizzare le emozioni, quindi a volte risultano socialmente inetti. La loro calma mortale rende ancora più difficile per loro relazionarsi con quelli che vedono come umani baseliner follemente focosi.\n\nI geni furono progettati migliaia di anni fa da una marina spaziale da tempo sciolta per ricoprire posizioni di ingegneria su grandi astronavi. Oggi, i geni prestano ancora servizio come ingegneri nelle grandi città e nelle flotte, ma molti si possono trovare anche a lavorare come avvocati, piloti e musicisti.</Genie.description>
  <!-- EN: Designed to be engineers, genies have natural aptitude with machines, and are emotionally cold and calm. They are also fragile and vulnerable to pain. Focused on machines, they often come off as socially inept. -->
  <Genie.descriptionShort>Progettati per essere ingegneri, i geni hanno un'attitudine naturale con le macchine e sono emotivamente freddi e calmi. Sono anche fragili e vulnerabili al dolore. Concentrati sulle macchine, spesso risultano socialmente inetti.</Genie.descriptionShort>
  
  <!-- EN: highmate -->
  <Highmate.label>highmate</Highmate.label>
  <!-- EN: Designed companions and concubines with a unique ability to psychically bond with a mate, highmates are empathic, beautiful, cheerful, and talented in social matters. They are also inept at manual tasks, physically weak, and mentally incapable of violence.\n\nOn a few wealthy worlds, highmate xenogerms are commercially available and some people become highmates as a sort of career. However, many societies find them abhorrent, either because they distract people from forming natural families, or because they are humans shaped to serve the pleasures of another. On such worlds they are either reserved as playthings of the powerful, or banned entirely. This particular line of highmate fits the fashions of classical Novaroma, but many other variants exist. -->
  <Highmate.description>Compagni e concubine progettati con una capacità unica di legarsi psichicamente con un compagno, gli highmate sono empatici, belli, allegri e talentuosi nelle questioni sociali. Sono anche inetti nei compiti manuali, fisicamente deboli e mentalmente incapaci di usare violenza.\n\nSu alcuni mondi ricchi, gli xenogermi highmate sono disponibili in commercio e alcune persone diventano highmate come una sorta di carriera. Tuttavia, molte società li trovano abominevoli, sia perché distraggono le persone dal formare famiglie naturali, sia perché sono esseri umani modellati per servire i piaceri di un altro. Su tali mondi sono riservati come giocattoli ai potenti o completamente banditi. Questa particolare linea di highmate si adatta allo stile classico di Novaroma, ma esistono molte altre varianti.</Highmate.description>
  <!-- EN: Designed companions and concubines with a unique ability to psychically bond with a mate, highmates are empathic, beautiful, cheerful, and talented in social matters. They are also inept at manual tasks, physically weak, and mentally incapable of violence. -->
  <Highmate.descriptionShort>Compagni e concubine progettati con una capacità unica di legarsi psichicamente con un compagno, gli highmate sono empatici, belli, allegri e talentuosi nelle questioni sociali. Sono anche inetti nei compiti manuali, fisicamente deboli e mentalmente incapaci di ricorrere alla violenza.</Highmate.descriptionShort>
  
  <!-- EN: hussar -->
  <Hussar.label>ussaro</Hussar.label>
  <!-- EN: Hussars are engineered soldiers. They fight aggressively and with precision, heal fast, thrive in extreme temperatures, and freely ingest military drugs. They have a genetic dependence on go-juice, which also makes them less likely to rebel against their commanders.\n\nWhile hussars' emotions make them dangerous in combat, they can't relate to baseliner humans. They are famous for their blood-red eyes and "hussar stare", a dead expression that unsettles many people. Their lack of expression and burning aggressive nature has led to many violent misunderstandings.\n\nIn most societies where they live, hussars are kept separated from the rest of the population. Hussars are single-purpose tools - and they generally aren't bothered by the fact. -->
  <Hussar.description>Gli ussari sono soldati ingegnerizzati. Combattono in modo aggressivo e preciso, guariscono velocemente, prosperano a temperature estreme e ingeriscono liberamente farmaci militari. Hanno una dipendenza genetica dal go-juice, che li rende anche meno propensi a ribellarsi ai loro comandanti.\n\nSebbene le emozioni degli ussari li rendano pericolosi in combattimento, non riescono a relazionarsi con gli umani baseliner. Sono famosi per i loro occhi rosso sangue e per lo "sguardo da ussaro", un'espressione morta che turba molte persone. La loro mancanza di espressione e la loro natura ardentemente aggressiva ha portato a molti violenti malintesi.\n\nNella maggior parte delle società in cui vivono, gli ussari vengono tenuti separati dal resto della popolazione. Gli ussari sono strumenti con un solo scopo e generalmente non se ne preoccupano.</Hussar.description>
  <!-- EN: Hussars are engineered soldiers. They fight aggressively and with precision, heal fast, thrive in extreme temperatures, and freely ingest military drugs. They have a genetic dependence on go-juice. -->
  <Hussar.descriptionShort>Gli ussari sono soldati ingegnerizzati. Combattono in modo aggressivo e preciso, guariscono velocemente, prosperano a temperature estreme e ingeriscono liberamente farmaci militari. Hanno una dipendenza genetica dal go-juice.</Hussar.descriptionShort>
  
  <!-- EN: impid -->
  <Impid.label>impid</Impid.label>
  <!-- EN: Made for desert life, impid cultures live on many rimworlds and dry deathworlds. Impids are extremely fast-moving, easily tolerate high temperatures, and can spew fire from their mouths. Though they are masters on the sand, impids struggle in other environments. They are terrible with farming. They fight well at range, but in close combat their physical weakness becomes apparent.\n\nOutlanders call them dustrunners because of their speed over open terrain and resistance to heat. Some tribes call them devils because of their horns and because they burn their enemies. Impid tribes' combat tactics usually center on rapid-approach incendiary attacks using both handheld fire weapons and their fire spew ability. -->
  <Impid.description>Creati per la vita nel deserto, le culture impid vivono su molti mondi marginali e mondi della morte aridi. Gli impid si muovono estremamente velocemente, tollerano facilmente le alte temperature e possono sputare fuoco dalla bocca. Sebbene siano padroni della sabbia, faticano in altri ambienti. Sono pessimi nell’agricoltura. Combattono bene a distanza, ma nel combattimento ravvicinato la loro debolezza fisica diventa evidente.\n\nGli stranieri li chiamano dustrunner per via della loro velocità sui terreni aperti e della resistenza al calore. Alcune tribù li chiamano diavoli per via delle loro corna e perché bruciano i nemici. Le tattiche di combattimento delle tribù impid di solito si concentrano su attacchi incendiari rapidi utilizzando sia armi da fuoco portatili che la loro capacità di sputare fuoco.</Impid.description>
  <!-- EN: Made for desert life, impids are very fast, can spew fire from their mouths, and easily tolerate high temperatures. They fight well at range, but in close combat they do little damage. They are terrible with farming, and have weak immune systems. -->
  <Impid.descriptionShort>Creati per la vita nel deserto, gli impid sono molto veloci, possono sputare fuoco dalla bocca e tollerano facilmente le alte temperature. Combattono bene a distanza, ma nel combattimento ravvicinato infliggono pochi danni. Sono terribili con l’agricoltura e hanno un sistema immunitario debole.</Impid.descriptionShort>
  
  <!-- EN: neanderthal -->
  <Neanderthal.label>neanderthal</Neanderthal.label>
  <!-- EN: Neanderthals are stocky, powerfully-built humanoids. Their most salient characteristic is that they are difficult to hurt: They are very resistant to injury, and their strong immune systems protect them from infection. However, without ever having evolved in a complex civilization, they are less adept than baseliner humans at intellectual and social tasks, and their impulsiveness can make them dangerously aggressive.\n\nHomo neanderthalensis was originally an archaic population of hominids that emerged over 200,000 years ago during the Pleistocene epoch. After they were replaced by and merged with humans 30,000 years ago, they were absent for tens of thousands of years until scientists resurrected them from ancient DNA. Neanderthals now survive in sub-societies on some settled planets. On the rimworlds, neanderthal tribes carve out the same existence as their Earth ancestors did so long ago. -->
  <Neanderthal.description>I neanderthal sono umanoidi robusti e di corporatura potente. La loro caratteristica più saliente è che sono difficili da ferire: sono molto resistenti alle lesioni e il loro forte sistema immunitario li protegge dalle infezioni. Tuttavia, senza essersi mai evoluti in una civiltà complessa, sono meno abili degli umani baseliner nei compiti intellettuali e sociali e la loro impulsività può renderli pericolosamente aggressivi.\n\nL'Homo neanderthalensis era originariamente una popolazione arcaica di ominidi emersa più di 200.000 anni fa durante l'epoca del Pleistocene. Dopo essere stati sostituiti e fusi con gli esseri umani 30.000 anni fa, sono rimasti assenti per decine di migliaia di anni finché gli scienziati non li hanno resuscitati dal DNA antico. I Neanderthal ora sopravvivono in sottosocietà su alcuni pianeti abitati. Sui rimworld, le tribù di Neanderthal si ritagliano la stessa esistenza dei loro antenati terrestri tanto tempo fa.</Neanderthal.description>
  <!-- EN: Neanderthals are stocky, powerfully-built humanoids. They are hardy and difficult to injure, and their strong immune systems protect them from infection. However, their minds are less adept at intellectual and social tasks, and their impulsiveness can make them dangerously aggressive. -->
  <Neanderthal.descriptionShort>I Neanderthal sono umanoidi robusti e di corporatura potente. Sono resistenti e difficili da ferire e il loro forte sistema immunitario li protegge dalle infezioni. Tuttavia, le loro menti sono meno abili nei compiti intellettuali e sociali e la loro impulsività può renderli pericolosamente aggressivi.</Neanderthal.descriptionShort>
  
  <!-- EN: pigskin -->
  <Pigskin.label>pigskin</Pigskin.label>
  <!-- EN: Pigskins are human-pig hybrids which are capable of two-legged movement, tool use, and speech, but which also retain many pig-like qualities. They are hardy and can eat almost anything without getting sick, but their trotter-shaped hands leave them at a disadvantage when attempting to precisely manipulate tools and objects. They don't see well at a distance, so pigskin gangs usually focus on close-range weapons. They also have a strong taste for explosives.\n\nPigskins were made for their organs. Uncomfortable with the idea of harvesting organs from baseliner humans, a long-gone government merged human DNA into pigs to make the animals produce more easily-transplantable hearts and lungs. They succeeded, but the resulting creatures became more humanlike than anyone anticipated. -->
  <Pigskin.description>I pigskin sono ibridi uomo-maiale capaci di muoversi su due zampe, usare strumenti e parlare, ma che conservano anche molte qualità simili a quelle dei maiali. Sono resistenti e possono mangiare quasi tutto senza ammalarsi, ma le loro mani a forma di zoccolo li mettono in svantaggio quando tentano di manipolare con precisione strumenti e oggetti. Non vedono bene a distanza, quindi le bande di pigskin di solito si concentrano sulle armi a distanza ravvicinata. Hanno anche una forte predilezione per gli esplosivi.\n\nI pigskin furono creati per i loro organi. A disagio con l’idea di prelevare organi da umani baseliner, un governo scomparso da tempo fuse il DNA umano con quello dei maiali per fare in modo che gli animali producessero cuori e polmoni più facilmente trapiantabili. Ci riuscirono, ma le creature risultanti divennero più simili agli umani di quanto chiunque si aspettasse.</Pigskin.description>
  <!-- EN: Pigskins are human-pig hybrids. They are hardy and can eat almost anything without getting sick, but their trotter-shaped hands are bad at fine manipulation. They don't see well at a distance, so they usually focus on close-range weapons. They have a strong taste for explosives. -->
  <Pigskin.descriptionShort>I pigskin sono ibridi uomo-maiale. Sono resistenti e possono mangiare quasi tutto senza ammalarsi, ma le loro mani a forma di zoccolo sono pessime nella manipolazione fine. Non vedono bene a distanza, quindi di solito si concentrano sulle armi a corto raggio. Hanno un forte gusto per gli esplosivi.</Pigskin.descriptionShort>
  
  <!-- EN: sanguophage -->
  <Sanguophage.label>sanguofago</Sanguophage.label>
  <!-- EN: Sanguophages are a type of archotech-enhanced xenohuman. Powered by archites, their abilities go far beyond normal genetic enhancements. They are mentally adept and preternaturally beautiful. In combat, they can launch deadly spines and heal injured friends. They don't age or die naturally and never suffer from disease or poison. A sanguophage can make a new sanguophage by reimplanting their own xenogerm into a person.\n\nSanguophages must regularly consume hemogen derived from human blood, and they must periodically deathrest for long periods. They're easily destroyed by fire, and slowed down by UV light.\n\nThe first sanguophage appeared thousands of years ago when the lord-explorer Varan-Dur sought to control a hyperintelligent archotech and found himself transformed by it instead. Every sanguophage is descended from him. Since then, sanguophages have often been hunted because of their destabilizing power and their need for blood. Since they can pass for baseliners, many live in hiding among typical humans.\n\nTheir numbers are unknown. Some think they are legends or rare irrelevancies. Some believe sanguophages secretly direct entire human civilizations. The stories speak of eternal lords ruling billions from slate-black space stations, or directing blood sacrifices at conferences in the underlayers of the deepest urbworlds. -->
  <Sanguophage.description>I sanguofagi sono un tipo di xenoumano potenziato dall'archotecnologia. Alimentati dagli architi, le loro abilità vanno ben oltre i normali miglioramenti genetici. Sono mentalmente abili e straordinariamente belli. In combattimento possono lanciare aculei mortali e curare gli amici feriti. Non invecchiano né muoiono naturalmente e non soffrono mai di malattie o veleni. Un sanguofago può creare un nuovo sanguofago reimpiantando il proprio xenogerme in una persona.\n\nI sanguofagi devono consumare regolarmente emogeno derivato dal sangue umano e devono periodicamente entrare in riposo di morte per lunghi periodi. Vengono facilmente distrutti dal fuoco e rallentati dalla luce UV.\n\nIl primo sanguofago apparve migliaia di anni fa quando il signore-esploratore Varan-Dur cercò di controllare un archotech iperintelligente e invece si ritrovò trasformato da esso. Da lui discende ogni sanguofago. Da allora i sanguofagi sono stati spesso cacciati a causa del loro potere destabilizzante e del loro bisogno di sangue. Dal momento che possono passare per baseliner, molti vivono nascosti tra gli umani comuni.\n\nIl loro numero è sconosciuto. Alcuni pensano che siano leggende o rare irrilevanze. Alcuni credono che i sanguofagi dirigano segretamente intere civiltà umane. Le storie parlano di signori eterni che governano miliardi da stazioni spaziali nere come l'ardesia, o che dirigono sacrifici di sangue in conferenze negli strati sotterranei dei mondi urbani più profondi.</Sanguophage.description>
  <!-- EN: Sanguophages are ageless, deathless super-humans powered by archotech-created archites in the bloodstream. They are beautiful and extremely intelligent. They can heal any injury, and never suffer from disease or poison. In combat, they can launch deadly spines and heal injured friends. The price is that sanguophages must consume hemogen derived from human blood to survive, and they must periodically deathrest for long periods. They're easily destroyed by fire, and slowed down by UV light. -->
  <Sanguophage.descriptionShort>I sanguofagi sono superumani senza età e immortali alimentati da architi creati dall'archotech nel flusso sanguigno. Sono belli ed estremamente intelligenti. Possono curare qualsiasi ferita e non soffrono mai di malattie o veleni. In combattimento possono lanciare aculei mortali e curare gli amici feriti. Il prezzo è che i sanguofagi devono consumare emogeno derivato dal sangue umano per sopravvivere e devono periodicamente entrare in riposo di morte per lunghi periodi. Vengono facilmente distrutti dal fuoco e rallentati dalla luce UV.</Sanguophage.descriptionShort>
  
  <!-- EN: waster -->
  <Waster.label>waster</Waster.label>
  <!-- EN: Wasters are aggressive, immune to toxic pollution, almost impervious to disease, and can ingest as much psychite and wake-up drugs as they wish with no ill effects. Their toxin-adapted metabolism means they must consume some form of psychite - usually flake or yayo.\n\nOriginally engineered to prevent resettlement of post-apocalyptic deathworlds, wasters are living area-denial weapons. Waster pirates armed with toxic weapons are the bane of many frontier peoples, both on the rimworlds and in the depths of the urbworld hyperstructures. -->
  <Waster.description>I waster sono aggressivi, immuni all'inquinamento tossico, quasi insensibili alle malattie e possono ingerire tutta la psichite e i farmaci per il risveglio che desiderano senza effetti negativi. Il loro metabolismo adattato alle tossine significa che devono consumare qualche forma di psichite, solitamente flake o yayo.\n\nOriginariamente progettati per prevenire il reinsediamento di mondi di morte post-apocalittici, i waster sono armi viventi di negazione d'area. I pirati waster armati di armi tossiche sono la rovina di molti popoli di frontiera, sia sui mondi rim che nelle profondità delle iperstrutture urbane.</Waster.description>
  <!-- EN: Wasters are aggressive, immune to toxic pollution, almost impervious to disease, and can ingest as much psychite and wake-up drugs as they wish with no ill effects. Their toxin-adapted metabolism means they must consume some form of psychite - usually flake or yayo. -->
  <Waster.descriptionShort>I waster sono aggressivi, immuni all'inquinamento tossico, quasi insensibili alle malattie e possono ingerire tutta la psichite e i farmaci per il risveglio che desiderano senza effetti negativi. Il loro metabolismo adattato alle tossine significa che devono consumare qualche forma di psichite, solitamente flake o yayo.</Waster.descriptionShort>
  
  <!-- EN: yttakin -->
  <Yttakin.label>yttakin</Yttakin.label>
  <!-- EN: Yttakin descend from colonists engineered to thrive on ultra-cold planets. Their great size and fur make them hardy in frozen environments. Yttakin share a psychic connection with the wildlife and can summon animals to their side during battles. They are not fast or energetic or precise, but can keep going when others would have collapsed long before.\n\nSince they migrated off their icy birthworld of Yttak, Yttakin settlements live on many planets. Their fur, roaring voices, and aversion to urban living sometimes leads naive outsiders to believe they are simple-minded animals. Quick-minded Yttakin are happy to make good use of such wrong beliefs, whether at the negotiating table or on the battlefield. -->
  <Yttakin.description>Gli yttakin discendono da coloni progettati per prosperare su pianeti ultrafreddi. Le loro grandi dimensioni e la pelliccia li rendono resistenti negli ambienti ghiacciati. Gli yttakin condividono una connessione psichica con la fauna selvatica e possono evocare animali al loro fianco durante le battaglie. Non sono veloci, energici o precisi, ma riescono ad andare avanti anche quando altri sarebbero crollati molto prima.\n\nDa quando sono migrati dal loro ghiacciato pianeta natale di Yttak, gli insediamenti yttakin vivono su molti pianeti. La loro pelliccia, le voci ruggenti e l'avversione per la vita urbana a volte portano estranei ingenui a credere che siano animali semplici. Gli yttakin, dalla mente pronta, sono felici di fare buon uso di tali convinzioni errate, sia al tavolo delle trattative che sul campo di battaglia.</Yttakin.description>
  <!-- EN: Yttakin descend from colonists engineered to thrive on ultra-cold planets. Their great size and fur make them hardy in frozen environments, and they have a unique ability to communicate vocally and psychically with animals. They are not fast or energetic or precise, but can keep going when others would have collapsed long before. -->
  <Yttakin.descriptionShort>Gli yttakin discendono da coloni progettati per prosperare su pianeti ultrafreddi. Le loro grandi dimensioni e la pelliccia li rendono resistenti negli ambienti ghiacciati e hanno una capacità unica di comunicare vocalmente e psichicamente con gli animali. Non sono veloci, energici o precisi, ma riescono ad andare avanti quando altri sarebbero crollati molto prima.</Yttakin.descriptionShort>
  
</LanguageData>