<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<LanguageData>
  
  <!-- EN: starjack -->
  <Starjack.label>starjack</Starjack.label>
  <!-- EN: Engineered for life among the stars, starjack are built to withstand the unforgiving conditions of deep space living. Their reflective pressure-adaptive skin provides insulation against extreme temperatures and allows them to survive brief exposure to hard vacuum. These adaptations make them invaluable for spacewalk repairs and emergency decompression scenarios.\n\nMost starjack spend their lives beyond planetary gravity, leading to lower muscle mass and reduced physical strength compared to baseline humans. However, their resilience in zero-gravity environments makes them essential for maintaining orbital platforms and working aboard long-haul vessels.\n\nAs one of humanity's oldest xenotypes, starjack played a crucial role in the colonization of space. They are a common sight on deep-space stations and interstellar ships, where genetic modification is often a more cost-effective solution than upgrading spacecraft to support unaltered human physiology. -->
  <Starjack.description>Progettati per la vita tra le stelle, gli starjack sono costruiti per resistere alle condizioni spietate della vita nello spazio profondo. La loro pelle riflettente e adattiva alla pressione fornisce isolamento contro le temperature estreme e permette loro di sopravvivere a una breve esposizione al vuoto. Questi adattamenti li rendono preziosi per le riparazioni extraveicolari e gli scenari di decompressione d'emergenza.\n\nLa maggior parte degli starjack trascorre la vita oltre la gravità planetaria, il che porta a una minore massa muscolare e a una ridotta forza fisica rispetto agli esseri umani di base. Tuttavia, la loro resilienza negli ambienti a gravità zero li rende essenziali per la manutenzione delle piattaforme orbitali e per il lavoro a bordo di navi a lungo raggio.\n\nCome uno dei più antichi xenotipi dell'umanità, gli starjack hanno svolto un ruolo cruciale nella colonizzazione dello spazio. Sono una presenza comune nelle stazioni spaziali profonde e sulle navi interstellari, dove la modifica genetica è spesso una soluzione più conveniente rispetto all'aggiornamento delle astronavi per supportare la fisiologia umana non modificata.</Starjack.description>
  <!-- EN: Engineered for life among the stars, starjack are built to withstand the unforgiving conditions of deep space living. Their reflective pressure-adaptive skin provides insulation against extreme temperatures and allows them to survive brief exposure to hard vacuum. -->
  <Starjack.descriptionShort>Progettati per la vita tra le stelle, gli starjack sono costruiti per resistere alle condizioni spietate dello spazio profondo. La loro pelle riflettente e adattiva alla pressione fornisce isolamento contro le temperature estreme e consente loro di sopravvivere a una breve esposizione al vuoto.</Starjack.descriptionShort>
  
</LanguageData>