<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<LanguageData>
  
  <!-- EN: The Anomaly -->
  <TheAnomaly.label>L'Anomalia</TheAnomaly.label>
  <!-- EN: Your research expedition has finally arrived at the source of the anomalous signal: an ancient archotech monolith on a distant planet. As you survey the structure from orbit, the scanner's audio feed forms garbled syllables which repeat your own name over and over. Your crewmate screams as her flesh begins flowing and reforming. A blinding beam of energy reaches up from the planet and tears your research vessel apart. You have disturbed something ancient and inhuman.\n\nNote: This is a difficult scenario and is not recommended for new players. -->
  <TheAnomaly.description>La tua spedizione scientifica è finalmente giunta sul lontano pianeta da cui proviene il segnale anomalo, emesso da un antico monolite archotech. Mentre osservi la struttura dall'orbita, lo scanner inizia a trasmettere una voce distorta che ripete incessantemente il tuo nome. Una compagna di equipaggio urla improvvisamente quando la sua carne comincia a liquefarsi e riformarsi. Un accecante raggio di energia si innalza dal pianeta e distrugge la tua nave di ricerca. Hai disturbato qualcosa di antico e disumano.\n\nNota: questo è uno scenario difficile e non è consigliato ai nuovi giocatori.</TheAnomaly.description>
  <!-- EN: Your research expedition has finally arrived at the source of the anomalous signal: an ancient archotech monolith on a distant planet. As you survey the structure from orbit, the scanner's audio feed forms garbled syllables which repeat your own name over and over. Your crewmate screams as her flesh begins flowing and reforming. A blinding beam of energy reaches up from the planet and tears your research vessel apart. You have disturbed something ancient and inhuman.\n\nNote: This is a difficult scenario and is not recommended for new players. -->
  <TheAnomaly.scenario.description>La tua spedizione scientifica è finalmente giunta sulla lontana pianeta da cui proviene il segnale anomalo, emesso da un antico monolite archotech. Mentre osservi la struttura dall'orbita, lo scanner inizia a trasmettere una voce distorta che ripete incessantemente il tuo nome. Una compagna di equipaggio urla improvvisamente quando la sua carne comincia a liquefarsi e riformarsi. Un accecante raggio di energia si innalza dal pianeta e distrugge la tua nave di ricerca. Hai disturbato qualcosa di antico e disumano.\n\nNota: questo è uno scenario difficile e non è consigliato ai nuovi giocatori.</TheAnomaly.scenario.description>
  <!-- EN: The Anomaly -->
  <TheAnomaly.scenario.name>L'Anomalia</TheAnomaly.scenario.name>
  <!-- EN: The ancient monolith unleashed an energy pulse that tore your research vessel apart and mutated your crew. Only a few of you made it to the escape pods.\n\nDespite the setback, your mission is far from over. If you can learn more about the monolith, perhaps you can find a way to shut it down - or harness its inhuman power. -->
  <TheAnomaly.scenario.parts.GameStartDialog.text>L'antico monolite ha sprigionato un impulso di energia che ha distrutto la tua nave di ricerca e mutato il tuo equipaggio. Solo pochi di voi sono riusciti a raggiungere le capsule di salvataggio.\n\nNonostante la battuta d'arresto, la tua missione è tutt'altro che finita. Se riuscirai a scoprire di più sul monolite, forse troverai un modo per disattivarlo... o sfruttarne il potere disumano.</TheAnomaly.scenario.parts.GameStartDialog.text>
  <!-- EN: Start with one ghoul and three colonists. -->
  <TheAnomaly.scenario.parts.ConfigurePawnsMutants.customSummary>Inizi con un ghoul e tre coloni.</TheAnomaly.scenario.parts.ConfigurePawnsMutants.customSummary>
  <!-- EN: Three researchers and a ghoul investigate an ancient monolith. -->
  <TheAnomaly.scenario.summary>Tre ricercatori e un ghoul indagano su un antico monolite.</TheAnomaly.scenario.summary>
  
</LanguageData>